Register of the Frank Angell papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Frank Angell papers
1900-1918
80142
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, memorabilia (1.6 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, notes, statistics, printed matter, personal documents, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to the work of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, the Comité National de Secours et d'Alimentation, and Frank Angell's involvement with both organizations. Materials document the relief work done in Belgium during World War I and its German occupation and Belgian unemployment relief before and during the war. Used as research material for the study by Angell, "The Belgians under the German Occupation," which is included in the collection.
Angell, Frank, 1857-1939.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1857 Born in Scituate, Rhode Island
1878 Graduated from the University of Vermont
1878-1880 Worked as English teacher to Chinese legation in Washington, D.C.
1880-1887 Worked as a physics teacher in a Washington, D.C. high school
1887 Went to Germany to do graduate work in physics, met psychologist Wilhelm Wundt, and switched field to psychology
1891 Graduated from Wundt's laboratory at the University of Leipzig with Ph.D. in psychology
1891-1892 Worked as Assistant Professor of Psychology at Cornell University
1892 Became Professor and Executive Head of the Department of Psychology at Stanford University
1895-1925 Associate Editor of the American Journal of Psychology
1915-1916 Worked for the Commission for Relief in Belgium and did relief work in Belgium
1919 Awarded the honor of Chevalier de l'Ordre de la Couronne by the King of Belgium
1922 Retired from Stanford University as Professor Emeritus
1928-1939 Associate editor of the Journal of General Psychology
1939 Died, in Palo Alto, California
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, correspondence, notes, statistics, printed matter, personal documents, photographs, and memorabilia relating to the work of the Commission for Relief in Belgium, the Comité National de Secours et d'Alimentation, and Frank Angell's involvement with both organizations. Materials document the relief work done in Belgium during World War I and its German occupation and Belgian unemployment relief before and during the war. Used as research material for the study by Angell, "The Belgians Under the German Occupation;" and the collection includes the typescript of the study.
Comité national de secours et d'alimentation (Brussels); Commission for Relief in Belgium (1914-1930); International relief.; Unemployed--Belgium.; World War, 1914-1918--Belgium.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.
- Photo Album, 1915 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Biographical File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes travel documents such as a passport, identification letter from Herbert Hoover, a travel permit from the German government, and a napkin.
- Biographical File, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  Includes notes, letters from provincial relief committees and the Commission for Relief in Belgium, and other personal correspondence to Frank Angell.
- Commission for Relief in Belgium File, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  Membership lists, circulars, a blank donation card, and letters of appreciation from the Pope and Archbishop.
- Marie Louise Marcy Subject File, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  Personal correspondence and a life certificate for Marie Louise Marcy.
- Speeches and Writings, 1915-1916
  - Reports and essays file, 1916 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    Personal notes, reports, drafts, and other writings by Frank Angell on unemployment, conditions, statistics, relief distributions, and other relief related issues during his time in Belgium that are unrelated to his study "Belgians Under German Occupation."
  - "Belgians Under German Occupation," File, Part I, circa 1916 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    Appendices, reports, essays, and other writings containing information on clothing relief, discreet assistance, shelter, unemployment, and other forms of aid used in "Belgians Under German Occupation."
  - "Belgians Under German Occupation," File, Part II, circa 1916 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    Drafts, reports, and other writings related to clothing relief, workhouses, relief categories, and other topics relating to aid used in "Belgians Under German Occupation."
  - "Belgians Under German Occupation," File, Part III, circa 1916 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    Table of contents and pages 1 through 90.
  - "Belgians Under German Occupation," File, Part IV, circa 1916 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    A third appendix and pages 91-183.
- Comité National de Secours et d'Alimentation File, 1914-1916
  Worksheets and forms used to construct a family profile, determine amount of goods and level of unemployment, and determine amount of relief received. Specific to each Belgian province or large municipality.
  - Circulars and correspondence File, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    Circulars to provincial and local committees on changes in policy and relief guidelines, correspondence between chairmen, pamphlets, reports, and specific instructions and dispatches from Comité de Secours et d'Alimentation and its national, provincial, and local branches. Topics include unemployment, disability, wage and rent prices, military families, pay periods, and public utility relief.
  - Reports on unemployment File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    Reports dealing with unemployment issued by the subcomittees Aide et Protection aux Chomeurs and Aide et Protection aux Sans-Travail Necessiteux.
  - Partial employment forms and claims File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    Certificates, forms, and worksheets used by the committee to determine eligibility for relief, partial employment, relief amounts, and steady employment.
  - Family profiles and declaration of goods File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2: 13)
- Relief Resources for Committee File, 1900-1916
  - Reports and circulars File, 1900-1916 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    Booklets, pamphlets, reports, circulars, and informational materials from certain local/provincial committees and interest groups, such as Federation Socialiste Societes de Secours Mutuels du Bassin de Charleroi and Metalworkers. Topics include new relief guidelines and distribution, record keeping, alcoholic drink tender, unemployment, and finances.
  - Worksheets and reference File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    Lists of relief recipients, charts to determine amounts of relief, expense reports, record keeping logs for relief recipients and unemployement, and other forms of reference and record keeping.
- Relief Resources for Citizens File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  Includes relief resources used by Belgian citizens, such as identification cards, identification books, relief tickets, certificates to receive aid, and statements of merchandise. All belong to one city or province.
- Comité National de Secours et Alimentation/Assistance Discrète File, 1915-1916
  - Letters from petitioners File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    Letters from petitioners seeking private aid from a benefactor to the Director/President; senders' names blacked out.
  - Photographs and Reports File, circa 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    Report describing "secours A" and photographs of women returning from/going to market.
- Statistics, 1913-1916
  - Maps, graphs, and calculations File, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    Comporised of wholly unemployed/partially unemployed statistics for specific provinces.
  - Charts File, 1913-1916 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    Charts of unemployment statistics for each province, numbers of children of unemployed, amounts of aid distributed by each province, and statistics for the Consultations de Nourrissons
- Medical Relief File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  Reports on various medical issues concerning Belgium, mainly tuberculosis and the distribution of aid and relief to combat the disease.
- Food relief File, 1906-1916 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  Contains photographs, rations calculations based on calories and costs, expense reports for weekly provisions/consumption of a certain family, and menus of meals provided to a certain family.
- Clothing Relief File, 1915-1916
  - Workhouses (Ouvroirs) File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    Reports and photographs of clothing workhouses, a label for workhouse shipments, and a program of lectures given to their employees.
  - Expense reports and order forms File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    Expense reports, order forms, inventory logs, distribution forms, and price listings for materials and already produced clothes.
- Housing Relief File, 1915-1916
  - Photographs, maps, and aeports File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    Photographs of homes, floor plans, general reports, maps of destroyed homes, expense reports, construction reports, lists of subsidies by province, construction budgets by province, and order forms relating to housing relief and the rebuilding of destroyed homes in Belgium.
  - Habitations provisoires dans la Province d'Anvers, 1915 (Box-folder 4: 1)
- Disability and War Relief File, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  Correspondence, worksheets, certificates, receipts, and statements for those who were disabled in the war or lost their main source of income due to the war.
- Children and Orphans Reports File, 1914-1916
  - Reports File, part I, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    Reports and statistics on bread lines, soup distribution, and other issues pertaining to children and orphans in various provinces.
  - Reports File, part II, 1914-1916 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    Reports on medical services and the general status of children and orphans in Antwerp.
  - Reports FIle, part III, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    Questionnaires, order forms, and worksheets for child relief and orphans, reports on orphanages, and reports on the activities of committees to aid children and orphans.
- Cantines Maternelles and Consultation de Nourrissons Subject File, circa 1916 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  Reports, flyers, and photographs that related to the relief organizations Cantines Maternelles and Consultations de Nourrissons, which both dealt with feeding and taking care of children/mothers/families.